<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
                    "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd"
[
<!ENTITY %  entities SYSTEM  "commonEntities.xml">
%entities;
]>
<!--

 Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one
 or more contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file
 distributed with this work for additional information
 regarding copyright ownership.  The ASF licenses this file
 to you under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the
 "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance
 with the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at

   http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

 Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing,
 software distributed under the License is distributed on an
 "AS IS" BASIS, WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY
 KIND, either express or implied.  See the License for the
 specific language governing permissions and limitations
 under the License.

-->

<chapter id="JMS-Client-0-8-Document-Scope-And-Intended-Audience">
  <title>Document Scope And Intended Audience</title>

  <para> The intended audience of this document is Java developers who are familiar with the JMS
    specification. Readers are not required to know all the details of AMQP protocols. However, some
    knowledge of AMQP basic concepts would be advantageous for reading of this document. </para>

  <para> This document only covers the usage of 0-8, 0-9 and 0-9-1 AMQP protocols with Qpid JMS
    client. The specifications for these protocols are available from the <ulink
      url="&amqpSrc;">AMQP web site</ulink>. </para>

  <para> The document covers some specific implementation details of JMS connections, sessions,
    consumers and producers in <xref linkend="JMS-Client-0-8-Client-Understanding"/>. It also
    demonstrates how to write a simple point to point and simple publish/subscribe application using
    Qpid JMS Client in <xref linkend="JMS-Client-0-8-Examples"/>. </para>

  <para>The Qpid JMS Client supports various configuration options which can be set via JVM system
    properties, connection URLs and JNDI configuration file. The setting of system properties is
    described in <xref linkend="JMS-Client-0-8-System-Properties"/>. The details of supported
    options within the connection URLs are given in <xref linkend="JMS-Client-0-8-Connection-URL"/>.
    The details of Qpid JMS client JNDI properties format is provided in <xref
      linkend="JMS-Client-0-8-JNDI-Properties-Format"/>. The Qpid destination URL format is covered
    in <xref linkend="JMS-Client-0-8-Binding-URL"/>. </para>

  <para>The Qpid JMS Client can be used for writing of JMS vendor neutral messaging applications.
    However, in some cases it might be required to use specific AMQP features. Thus, the Qpid client
    provides the extended operation set to invoke those features. </para>

  <para>
    <xref linkend="JMS-Client-0-8-Logging"/> provides the details about turning on client logging
    which can help in debugging of various issues while developing the messaging applications. </para>

  <para>The details about Qpid JMS Client Exceptions are provided in <xref
      linkend="JMS-Client-0-8-Appendix-Exceptions"/></para>

</chapter>
