<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!--

 Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one
 or more contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file
 distributed with this work for additional information
 regarding copyright ownership.  The ASF licenses this file
 to you under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the
 "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance
 with the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at

   http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

 Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing,
 software distributed under the License is distributed on an
 "AS IS" BASIS, WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY
 KIND, either express or implied.  See the License for the
 specific language governing permissions and limitations
 under the License.

-->

<section id="Java-Broker-Concepts-Virtualhosts">
  <title>Virtualhosts</title>
  <para>A virtualhost is a namespace in which messaging is performed. Virtualhosts are independent;
    the messaging goes on a within a virtualhost is independent of any messaging that goes on in
    another virtualhost. For instance, a queue named <emphasis>foo</emphasis> defined in one
    virtualhost is completely independent of a queue named <emphasis>foo</emphasis> in another
    virtualhost.</para>
  <para>A virtualhost is identified by a name which must be unique broker-wide. Clients use the name
    to identify the virtualhost to which they wish to connect when they connect.</para>
  <para>A virtualhost exists in a container called a virtualhost node.</para>
  <para>The virtualhost comprises of a number of entities. This section summaries the purpose of
    each of the entities and describes the relationships between them. These details are developed
    further in the sub-sections that follow.</para>
  <para><emphasis>Exchanges</emphasis> is a named entity within the Virtual Host which receives
    messages from producers and routes them to matching Queues.</para>
  <para><emphasis>Queues</emphasis> are named entities that hold messages for delivery to consumer
    applications.</para>
  <para><emphasis>Bindings</emphasis> are relationships between Exchanges and Queue that facilitate
    routing of messages from the Exchange to the Queue.</para>
  <para><emphasis>Connections</emphasis> represent a live connection to the virtualhost from a
    messaging client.</para>
  <para>A <emphasis>Session</emphasis> represents a context for the production or consumption of
    messages. Connection support many Sessions.</para>
  <para>A <emphasis>Consumer</emphasis> represents a live consumer that is attached to queue.</para>
  <para> The following diagram depicts the Virtualhost model: <figure>
      <title>Virtualhost Model</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/VirtualHost-Model.png" format="PNG" scalefit="1"/>
        </imageobject>
        <textobject>
          <phrase>Virtual Host Model</phrase>
        </textobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
  </para>
  <para>A <emphasis>virtualhost</emphasis> is backed by storage which is used to store the messages.</para>
</section>
