<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE section PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
                    "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<!--

 Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one
 or more contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file
 distributed with this work for additional information
 regarding copyright ownership.  The ASF licenses this file
 to you under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the
 "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance
 with the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at

   http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

 Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing,
 software distributed under the License is distributed on an
 "AS IS" BASIS, WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY
 KIND, either express or implied.  See the License for the
 specific language governing permissions and limitations
 under the License.

-->
<section id="Java-Broker-Security-External-Provider">
    <title>External (SSL Client Certificates)</title>

    <para> When <link linkend="Java-Broker-Management-Managing-Truststores"> requiring SSL Client
        Certificates</link> be presented the External Authentication Provider can be used, such that
        the user is authenticated based on trust of their certificate alone, and the X500Principal
        from the SSL session is then used as the username for the connection, instead of also
        requiring the user to present a valid username and password. </para>

    <para>
        <emphasis role="bold">Note:</emphasis> The External Authentication Provider should typically
        only be used on the AMQP/HTTP ports, in conjunction with <link
            linkend="Java-Broker-Management-Managing-Ports">SSL client certificate
            authentication</link>. It is not intended for other uses such as the JMX management port and
        will treat any non-sasl authentication processes on these ports as successful with the given
        username. As such you should configure another Authentication Provider for use on JMX
        ports.</para>

    <para>On creation of External Provider the use of full DN or username CN as a principal name can
        be configured. If attribute "Use the full DN as the Username" is set to "true" the full DN is
        used as an authenticated principal name. If attribute "Use the full DN as the Username" is set
        to "false" the user name CN part is used as the authenticated principal name. Setting the
        field to "false" is particular useful when <link linkend="Java-Broker-Security-ACLs"
            >ACL</link> is required, as at the moment, ACL does not support commas in the user name.
    </para>
</section>

