<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!--

Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one
or more contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file
distributed with this work for additional information
regarding copyright ownership.  The ASF licenses this file
to you under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the
"License"); you may not use this file except in compliance
with the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at

http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing,
software distributed under the License is distributed on an
"AS IS" BASIS, WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY
KIND, either express or implied.  See the License for the
specific language governing permissions and limitations
under the License.

-->

<section>
  <title>Queue Replication with the HA module</title>
  <para>
    As well as support for an active-passive cluster, the <filename>ha</filename> module
    also allows you to replicate individual queues. The <firstterm>original</firstterm>
    queue is used as normal.  The <firstterm>replica</firstterm> queue is updated
    automatically as messages are added to or removed from the original queue.
  </para>
  <para>
    To create a replica you need the HA module to be loaded on both the orignal and replica
    brokers. Note that it is not safe to modify the replica queue other than via the
    automatic updates from the original. Adding or removing messages on the replica queue
    will make replication inconsistent and may cause message loss. The HA module does
    <emphasis>not</emphasis> enforce restricted access to the replica queue (as it does in
    the case of a cluster) so it is up to the application to ensure the replca is not used
    until it has been disconnected from the original.
  </para>
  <para>
    Suppose that <command>myqueue</command> is a queue on <command>node1</command> and
    we want to create a replica of <command>myqueue</command> on <command>node2</command>
    (where both brokers are using the default AMQP port.) This is accomplished by the command:
    <programlisting>
      qpid-config --broker=node2 add queue --start-replica node1 myqueue
    </programlisting>
  </para>
  <para>
    If <command>myqueue</command> already exists on the replica broker you  can start replication from the original queue like this:
    <programlisting>
      qpid-ha replicate -b node2 node1 myqueue
    </programlisting>
  </para>
</section>
