<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<chapter xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><title>
      Apache Qpid : Management Console Security
    </title><section role="h1" id="ManagementConsoleSecurity-ManagementConsoleSecurity"><title>
            Management
            Console Security
          </title>
            <itemizedlist>
              <listitem><para>
                <xref linkend="ManagementConsoleSecurity-SSLencryptedRMI-280.5andabove-29"/>
              </para></listitem>
              <listitem><para>
                <xref linkend="ManagementConsoleSecurity-JMXMP-28M4andprevious-29"/>
              </para></listitem>
              <listitem><para>
                <xref linkend="ManagementConsoleSecurity-UserAccounts-26AccessRights"/>
              </para></listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
          <section role="h2" id="ManagementConsoleSecurity-SSLencryptedRMI-280.5andabove-29"><title>
            SSL
            encrypted RMI (0.5 and above)
          </title>
	  <para>
            Current versions of the broker make use of SSL encryption to
            secure their RMI based JMX ConnectorServer for security purposes.
            This ships enabled by default, although the test SSL keystore
            used during development is not provided for security reasons
            (using this would provide no security as anyone could have access
            to it).
          </para><section role="h3" id="ManagementConsoleSecurity-BrokerConfiguration"><title>
            Broker
            Configuration
          </title>

	  <para>
            The broker configuration must be updated before the broker will
            start. This can be done either by disabling the SSL support,
            utilizing a purchased SSL certificate to create a keystore of
            your own, or using the example 'create-example-ssl-stores' script
            in the brokers bin/ directory to generate a self-signed keystore.
          </para><para>
            The broker must be configured with a keystore containing the
            private and public keys associated with its SSL certificate. This
            is accomplished by setting the Java environment properties
            <emphasis>javax.net.ssl.keyStore</emphasis> and
            <emphasis>javax.net.ssl.keyStorePassword</emphasis> respectively with the
            location and password of an appropriate SSL keystore. Entries for
            these properties exist in the brokers main configuration file
            alongside the other management settings (see below), although the
            command line options will still work and take precedence over the
            configuration file.
          </para>
            <programlisting>
&lt;management&gt;
    &lt;ssl&gt;
        &lt;enabled&gt;true&lt;/enabled&gt;
        &lt;!-- Update below path to your keystore location, eg ${conf}/qpid.keystore  --&gt;
        &lt;keyStorePath&gt;${prefix}/../test_resources/ssl/keystore.jks&lt;/keyStorePath&gt;
        &lt;keyStorePassword&gt;password&lt;/keyStorePassword&gt;
    &lt;/ssl&gt;
&lt;/management&gt;
</programlisting>
<!--h3--></section>

          <section role="h3" id="ManagementConsoleSecurity-JMXManagementConsoleConfiguration"><title>
            JMX
            Management Console Configuration
          </title>

	  <para>
            If the broker makes use of an SSL certificate signed by a known
            signing CA (Certification Authority), the management console
            needs no extra configuration, and will make use of Java's
            built-in CA
            truststore for certificate verification (you may however have to
            update the system-wide default truststore if your CA is not
            already present in it).
          </para><para>
            If however you wish to use a self-signed SSL certificate, then
            the management console must be provided with an SSL truststore
            containing a record for the SSL certificate so that it is able to
            validate it when presented by the broker. This is performed by
            setting the <emphasis>javax.net.ssl.trustStore</emphasis> and
            <emphasis>javax.net.ssl.trustStorePassword</emphasis> environment variables
            when starting the console. This can be done at the command line,
            or alternatively an example configuration has been made within
            the console's qpidmc.ini launcher configuration file that may
            pre-configured in advance for repeated usage. See the <xref linkend="qpid_Qpid-20JMX-20Management-20Console-20User-20Guide"/> for more
            information on this configuration process.
          </para>
<!--h3--></section>

	  <section role="h3" id="ManagementConsoleSecurity-JConsoleConfiguration"><title>
            JConsole
            Configuration
          </title>

	  <para>
            As with the JMX Management Console above, if the broker is using
            a self-signed SSL certificate then in order to connect remotely
            using JConsole, an appropriate trust store must be provided at
            startup. See <xref linkend="qpid_JConsole"/> for further details on configuration.
          </para>
<!--h3--></section>

	  <section role="h3" id="ManagementConsoleSecurity-AdditionalInformation"><title>
            Additional
            Information
          </title>

	  <para>
            More information on Java's handling of SSL certificate
            verification and customizing the keystores can be found in the
            <xref linkend="qpid_JSSERefGuide"/> .
          </para>
<!--h3--></section>
<!--h2--></section>

	  

	  <section role="h2" id="ManagementConsoleSecurity-JMXMP-28M4andprevious-29"><title>
            JMXMP
            (M4 and previous)
          </title>

	  <para>
            In previous releases of Qpid (M4 and below) the broker, can make
            use of Sun's Java Management Extensions Messaging Protocol
            (JMXMP) to provide encryption of the JMX connection, offering
            increased security over the default unencrypted RMI based JMX
            connection.
          </para><section role="h3" id="ManagementConsoleSecurity-DownloadandInstall"><title>
            Download and
            Install
          </title>

	  <para>
            This is possible by adding the jmxremote_optional.jar as provided
            by Sun. This jar is covered by the Sun Binary Code License and is
            not compatible with the Apache License which is why this
            component is not bundled with Qpid.
          </para><para>
            Download the JMX Remote API 1.0.1_04 Reference Implementation
            from <xref linkend="qpid_download.jsp"/>. The included
            'jmxremote-1_0_1-bin\lib\jmxremote_optional.jar' file must be
            added to the broker classpath:
          </para><para>
            First set your classpath to something like this:
          </para>
            <programlisting>
CLASSPATH=jmxremote_optional.jar
</programlisting>
          <para>
            Then, run qpid-server passing the following additional flag:
          </para>
            <programlisting>
qpid-server -run:external-classpath=first
</programlisting>
          <para>
            Following this the configuration option can be updated to enabled
            use of the JMXMP based JMXConnectorServer.
          </para>
<!--h3--></section>

	  <section role="h3" id="ManagementConsoleSecurity-BrokerConfiguration"><title>
            Broker
            Configuration
          </title>

	  <para>
            To enabled this security option change the
            <emphasis>security-enabled</emphasis> value in your broker configuration
            file.
          </para>
            <programlisting>
    &lt;management&gt;
        &lt;security-enabled&gt;true&lt;/security-enabled&gt;
    &lt;/management&gt;
</programlisting>
          <para>
            You may also (for M2 and earlier) need to set the following
            system properties using the environment variable QPID_OPTS:
          </para><para>
            QPID_OPTS="-Dcom.sun.management.jmxremote
            -Dcom.sun.management.jmxremote.port=8999
            -Dcom.sun.management.jmxremote.authenticate=false
            -Dcom.sun.management.jmxremote.ssl=false"
          </para>
<!--h3--></section>

	  <section role="h3" id="ManagementConsoleSecurity-JMXManagementConsoleConfiguration"><title>
            JMX
            Management Console Configuration
          </title>

	  <para>
            If you wish to connect to a broker configured to use JMXMP then
            the console also requires provision of the Optional sections of
            the JMX Remote API that are not included within the JavaSE
            platform.
          </para><para>
            In order to make it available to the console, place the
            'jmxremote_optional.jar' (rename the file if any additional
            information is present in the file name) jar file within the
            'plugins/jmxremote.sasl_1.0.1/' folder of the console release (on
            Mac OS X you will need to select 'Show package contents' from the
            context menu whilst selecting the management console bundle in
            order to reveal the inner file tree).
          </para><para>
            Following the the console will automatically load the JMX Remote
            Optional classes and attempt the JMXMP connection when connecting
            to a JMXMP enabled broker.
          </para>
<!--h3--></section>
<!--h2--></section>

	  <section role="h2" id="ManagementConsoleSecurity-UserAccounts-26AccessRights"><title>
            User
            Accounts &amp; Access Rights
          </title>

	  <para>
            In order to access the management operations via JMX, users must
            have an account and have been assigned appropriate access rights.
            See <xref linkend="qpid_Configuring-20Management-20Users"/>
          </para>
<!--h2--></section>
<!--h1--></section>

	  
</chapter>
