<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<chapter xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><title>
      Apache Qpid : Starting a cluster
    </title><section role="h1" id="Startingacluster-RunningaQpiddcluster"><title>
            Running a
            Qpidd cluster
          </title>
          <para>
            There are several pre-requisites to running a qpidd cluster:
          </para><section role="h2" id="Startingacluster-Installandconfigureopenais-2Fcorosync"><title>
            Install
            and configure openais/corosync
          </title>
          <para>
            Qpid clustering uses a multicast protocol provided by the
            corosync (formerly called openais) library. Install whichever is
            available on your OS.
            E.g. in fedora10: yum install corosync.
          </para><para>
            The configuration file is /etc/ais/openais.conf on openais,
            /etc/corosync.conf on early corosync versions and
            /etc/corosync/corosync.conf on recent corosync versions. You will
            need to edit the default file created when you installed
          </para><para>
            Here is an example, with places marked that you will
            change. ( Below, I will describe how to change the file. )
          </para>
            <programlisting>
# Please read the openais.conf.5 manual page

totem {
        version: 2
        secauth: off
        threads: 0
        interface {
                ringnumber: 0
                ## You must change this address ##
                bindnetaddr: 20.0.100.0
                mcastaddr: 226.94.32.36
                mcastport: 5405
        }
}

logging {
        debug: off
        timestamp: on
        to_file: yes
        logfile: /tmp/aisexec.log
}

amf {
        mode: disabled
}
</programlisting>
          <para>
            You must sent the bindnetaddr entry in the configuration file to
            the network address of your network interface. This must be a
            real network interface, not the loopback address 127.0.0.1
          </para><para>
            You can find your network interface by running ifconfig. This
            will list the address and the mask, e.g.
          </para>
            <programlisting>
inet addr:20.0.20.32  Bcast:20.0.20.255  Mask:255.255.255.0
</programlisting>
          <para>
            The bindnetaddr is the logical AND of the inet addr and mask
            values, in the example above 20.0.20.0
          </para>
<!--h2--></section>

	  <section role="h2" id="Startingacluster-Openyourfirewall"><title>
            Open your
            firewall
          </title>
          <para>
            In the above example file, I use mcastport 5405.
            This implies that your firewall must allow UDP
            protocol over port 5405, or that you disable the firewall
          </para>
	  <!--h2--></section>

	  <section role="h2" id="Startingacluster-Usetheproperidentity."><title>
            Use the
            proper identity.
          </title>
          <para>
            The qpidd process must be started with the correct identity in
            order to use the corosync/openais library.
          </para><para>
            For openais and early corosync versions the installation of
            openAIS/corosync on your system will create a new
            group called "ais". The user that starts the qpidd processes of
            the cluster
            must have "ais" as its effective group id. You can create a user
            specifically for this purpose with ais as the primary group,
            or
            a user that has ais as a secondary group can use "newgrp" to set
            the primary group to ais when running qpidd.
          </para><para>
            For recent corosync versions you no longer need to set your group
            to "ais" but you do need to create a file in
            /etc/corosync/uidgid.d/ to allow access for whatever user/group
            ID you want to use. For example create
            /etc/corosync/uidgid.d/qpid th the contents:
          </para>
            <programlisting>
uidgid {
   uid: qpid
   gid: qpid
}
</programlisting>
<!--h2--></section>


          <section role="h2" id="Startingacluster-StartingaCluster"><title>
            Starting a
            Cluster
          </title>
          <para>
            To be a member of a cluster you must pass the --cluster-name
            argument to qpidd. This is the only required option to join
            a  cluster, other options can be set as for a normal qpidd.
          </para><para>
            For example to start a cluster of 3 brokers on the current
            host
            Here is an example of starting a cluster of 3 members, all on the
            current host but with different ports and different log files:
          </para>
            <programlisting>
qpidd -p5672 --cluster-name=MY_CLUSTER --log-output=cluster0.log -d --no-data-dir --auth=no
qpidd -p5673 --cluster-name=MY_CLUSTER --log-output=cluster0.log -d --no-data-dir --auth=no
qpidd -p5674 --cluster-name=MY_CLUSTER --log-output=cluster0.log -d --no-data-dir --auth=no
</programlisting>
          <para>
            In a deployed system, cluster members will normally be on
            different hosts but for development its useful to be able to
            create a cluster on a single host.
          </para>
	  <!--h2--></section>

	  <section role="h2" id="Startingacluster-SELinuxconflicts"><title>
            SELinux conflicts
          </title>
          <para>
            Developers will often start openais/corosync as a service like
            this:
          </para><para>
            service openais start
          </para><para>
            But will then will start a cluster-broker without using the
            service script like this:
          </para><para>
            /usr/sbin/qpidd --cluster-name my_cluster ...
          </para><para>
            If SELinux is in enforcing mode this may cause qpidd to hang due
            because of the different SELinux contexts.
            There are 3 ways to resolve this:
          </para><itemizedlist>
            <listitem><para>run both qpidd and openais/corosync as services.
            </para></listitem>
            <listitem><para>run both qpidd and openais/corosync as user processes.
            </para></listitem>
            <listitem><para>make selinux permissive:
            </para></listitem>
          </itemizedlist><para>
            To check what mode selinux is running:
          </para>
            <programlisting>
# getenforce
</programlisting>
          <para>
            To change the mode:
          </para>
            <programlisting>
# setenforce permissive
</programlisting>
          <para>
            Note that in a deployed system both openais/corosync and qpidd
            should be started as services, in which case there is no problem
            with SELinux running in enforcing mode.
          </para>
	  <!--h2--></section>

	  <section role="h2" id="Startingacluster-Troubleshootingchecklist."><title>
            Troubleshooting
            checklist.
          </title>
          <para>
            If you have trouble starting your cluster, make sure that:
          </para><para>
            1. You have edited the correct openais/corosync configuration
            file and set bindnetaddr correctly
            1. Your firewall allows UDP on the openais/corosync
            mcastport
            2. Your effective group is "ais" (openais/old corosync) or you
            have created an appropriate ID file (new corosync)
            3. Your firewall allows TCP on the ports used by qpidd.
            4. If you're starting openais as a service but running qpidd
            directly, ensure selinux is in permissive mode
          </para>
<!--h2--></section>
<!--h1--></section>
</chapter>
