<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!--
 
 Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one
 or more contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file
 distributed with this work for additional information
 regarding copyright ownership.  The ASF licenses this file
 to you under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the
 "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance
 with the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at
 
   http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0
 
 Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing,
 software distributed under the License is distributed on an
 "AS IS" BASIS, WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY
 KIND, either express or implied.  See the License for the
 specific language governing permissions and limitations
 under the License.
 
-->

<chapter xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><title>
      Apache Qpid : Use Priority Queues
    </title>

    
    <section role="h2" id="UsePriorityQueues-GeneralInformation"><title>
            General
            Information
          </title>
	  <para>
            The Qpid M3 release introduces priority queues into the Java
            Messaging Broker, supporting JMS clients who wish to make use of
            priorities in their messaging implementation.
          </para><para>
            There are some key points around the use of priority queues in
            Qpid, discussed in the sections below.
          </para>
<!--h2--></section>
    <section role="h2" id="UsePriorityQueues-DefiningPriorityQueues"><title>
            Defining
            Priority Queues
          </title>
	  <para>
            You must define a priority queue specifically before you start to
            use it. You cannot subsequently change a queue to/from a priority
            queue (without deleting it and re-creating).
          </para><para>
            You define a queue as a priority queue in the virtualhost
            configuration file, which the broker loads at startup. When
            defining the queue, add a &lt;priority&gt;true&lt;/priority&gt;
            element. This will ensure that the queue has 10 distinct
            priorities, which is the number supported by JMS.
          </para><para>
            If you require fewer priorities, it is possible to specify a
            &lt;priorities&gt;int&lt;/priorities&gt; element (where int is a
            valid integer value between 2 and 10 inclusive) which will give
            the queue that number of distinct priorities. When messages are
            sent to that queue, their effective priority will be calculated
            by partitioning the priority space. If the number of effective
            priorities is 2, then messages with priority 0-4 are treated the
            same as "lower priority" and messages with priority 5-9 are
            treated equivalently as "higher priority".
          </para>
            <programlisting>
&lt;queue&gt;
    &lt;name&gt;test&lt;/name&gt;
    &lt;test&gt;
        &lt;exchange&gt;amq.direct&lt;/exchange&gt;
        &lt;priority&gt;true&lt;/priority&gt;
    &lt;/test&gt;
&lt;/queue&gt;
</programlisting>
<!--h2--></section>
          
    <section role="h2" id="UsePriorityQueues-Clientconfiguration-2Fmessagingmodelforpriorityqueues"><title>
            Client configuration/messaging model for priority queues
          </title>
	  <para>
            There are some other configuration &amp; paradigm changes which
            are required in order that priority queues work as expected.
          </para>
    <section role="h3" id="UsePriorityQueues-Setlowprefetch"><title>
            Set low pre-fetch
          </title>
	  <para>
            Qpid clients receive buffered messages in batches, sized
            according to the pre-fetch value. The current default is 5000.
          </para><para>
            However, if you use the default value you will probably
            <emphasis>not</emphasis> see desirable behaviour with messages of different
            priority. This is because a message arriving after the pre-fetch
            buffer has filled will not leap frog messages of lower priority.
            It will be delivered at the front of the next batch of buffered
            messages (if that is appropriate), but this is most likely NOT
            what you need.
          </para><para>
            So, you need to set the prefetch values for your client
            (consumer) to make this sensible. To do this set the java system
            property max_prefetch on the client environment (using -D) before
            creating your consumer.
          </para><para>
            Setting the Qpid pre-fetch to 1 for your client means that
            message priority will be honoured by the Qpid broker as it
            dispatches messages to your client. A default for all client
            connections can be set via a system property:
          </para>
            <programlisting>
-Dmax_prefetch=1
</programlisting>
          <para>
            The prefetch can be also be adjusted on a per connection basis by
            adding a 'maxprefetch' value to the <xref linkend="qpid_Connection-20URL-20Format"/>
          </para>
            <programlisting>
amqp://guest:guest@client1/development?maxprefetch='1'&amp;brokerlist='tcp://localhost:5672'
</programlisting>
          <para>
            There is a slight performance cost here if using the receive()
            method and you could test with a slightly higher pre-fetch (up to
            10) if the trade-off between throughput and prioritisation is
            weighted towards the former for your application. (If you're
            using OnMessage() then this is not a concern.)
          </para>
<!--h3--></section>
    <section role="h3" id="UsePriorityQueues-Singleconsumerpersession"><title>
            Single
            consumer per session
          </title>
	  <para>
            If you are using the receive() method to consume messages then
            you should also only use one consumer per session with priority
            queues. If you're using OnMessage() then this is not a concern.
          </para>
<!--h3--></section>
<!--h2--></section>
</chapter>
