<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!--

 Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one
 or more contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file
 distributed with this work for additional information
 regarding copyright ownership.  The ASF licenses this file
 to you under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the
 "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance
 with the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at

   http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

 Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing,
 software distributed under the License is distributed on an
 "AS IS" BASIS, WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY
 KIND, either express or implied.  See the License for the
 specific language governing permissions and limitations
 under the License.

-->

<section id="Java-Broker-Concepts-Exchanges">
<title>Exchanges</title>
 <para>An <emphasis>Exchange</emphasis> is a named entity within the <emphasis>Virtualhost</emphasis> which receives
  messages from producers and routes them to matching <emphasis>Queue</emphasis>s within the <emphasis>Virtualhost</emphasis>.</para>
 <para>The server provides a set of exchange types with each exchange type implementing a different routing algorithm. For details of how
  these exchanges types work see <xref linkend="Java-Broker-Concepts-Exchanges-Types"/> below.</para>
 <para>The server predeclares a number of exchange instances with names starting with &quot;<literal>amq.</literal>&quot;. These are defined in
  <xref linkend="Java-Broker-Concepts-Exchanges-Predeclared"/>.</para>
 <para>Applications can make use the pre-declared exchanges, or they may declare their own. The number of exchanges within a virtual host is
  limited only by resource constraints.</para>
 <para>The behaviour when an exchange is unable to route a message to any queue is defined in <xref linkend="Java-Broker-Concepts-Exchanges-UnroutableMessage"/></para>
 <section id="Java-Broker-Concepts-Exchanges-Predeclared">
  <title>Predeclared Exchanges</title>
  <para>Each virtual host pre-declares the following exchanges:
   <itemizedlist>
    <listitem><para>amq.direct (an instance of a direct exchange)</para></listitem>
    <listitem><para>amq.topic (an instance of a topic exchange)</para></listitem>
    <listitem><para>amq.fanout (an instance of a fanout exchange)</para></listitem>
    <listitem><para>amq.match (an instance of a headers exchange)</para></listitem>
   </itemizedlist>
  </para>
  <para>The conceptual &quot;<literal>default exchange</literal>&quot; always exists, effectively a special instance of
   direct exchange which uses the empty string as its name. All queues are automatically bound to it upon their creation
   using the queue name as the binding key, and unbound upon their deletion. It is not possible to manually add or remove
   bindings within this exchange.</para>
  <para>Applications may not declare exchanges with names beginning with &quot;<literal>amq.</literal>&quot;. Such names are reserved for system use.</para>
 </section>
 <section id="Java-Broker-Concepts-Exchanges-Types">
  <title>Exchange Types</title>
  <para>
   The following Exchange types are supported.
   <itemizedlist>
    <listitem><para>Direct</para></listitem>
    <listitem><para>Topic</para></listitem>
    <listitem><para>Fanout</para></listitem>
    <listitem><para>Headers</para></listitem>
   </itemizedlist>
   These exchange types are described in the following sub-sections.</para>

   <section id="Java-Broker-Concepts-Exchanges-Types-Direct">
   <title>Direct</title>
   <para>The direct exchange type routes messages to queues based on an exact match between
    the routing key of the message, and the binding key used to bind the queue to the exchange. Additional
    filter rules may be specified using a <link linkend="Java-Broker-Concepts-Exchanges-BindingArguments-JMSSelector">
    binding argument specifying a JMS message selector</link>.
   </para>
   <para>This exchange type is often used to implement point to point messaging. When used in this manner, the normal
   convention is that the binding key matches the name of the queue. It is also possible to use this exchange type
   for multi-cast, in this case the same binding key is associated with many queues.</para>
   <figure>
    <title>Direct exchange</title>
    <mediaobject>
     <imageobject>
      <imagedata fileref="images/Exchange-Direct.png" format="PNG" scalefit="1"/>
     </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
   </figure>
   <para>The figure above illustrates the operation of direct exchange type. The yellow messages published with the routing key
    &quot;<literal>myqueue</literal>&quot; match the binding key corresponding to queue &quot;<literal>myqueue</literal>&quot; and so are routed there.  The red
    messages published with the routing key &quot;<literal>foo</literal>&quot; match two bindings in the table so a copy of the message is
    routed to both the &quot;<literal>bar1</literal>&quot; and &quot;<literal>bar2</literal>&quot; queues.</para>
    <para>The routing key of the blue message matches no binding keys, so the message is unroutable. It is handled as described
     in <xref linkend="Java-Broker-Concepts-Exchanges-UnroutableMessage"/>.</para>
  </section>
  <section id="Java-Broker-Concepts-Exchanges-Types-Topic">
    <title>Topic</title>
    <para>This exchange type is used to support the classic publish/subscribe paradigm.</para>
    <para>The topic exchange is capable of routing messages to queues based on wildcard matches between the routing key and the
     binding key pattern defined by the queue binding. Routing keys are formed from one or more words, with each word delimited
     by a full-stop (.). The pattern matching characters are the * and # symbols. The * symbol matches a single word  and the #
     symbol matches zero or more words.</para>
   <para>Additional filter rules may be specified using a <link linkend="Java-Broker-Concepts-Exchanges-BindingArguments-JMSSelector">
     binding argument specifying a JMS message selector</link>.</para>
   <para>The following three figures help explain how the topic exchange functions.</para>
    <para></para>
    <figure>
     <title>Topic exchange - exact match on topic name</title>
     <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
       <imagedata fileref="images/Exchange-Topic.png" format="PNG" scalefit="1"/>
      </imageobject>
     </mediaobject>
    </figure>
   <para>The figure above illustrates publishing messages with routing key &quot;<literal>weather</literal>&quot;. The exchange routes each
    message to every bound queue whose binding key matches the routing key.</para>
   <para>In the case illustrated, this means that each subscriber's queue receives every yellow message.</para>
   <figure>
    <title>Topic exchange - matching on hierarchical topic patterns</title>
    <mediaobject>
     <imageobject>
      <imagedata fileref="images/Exchange-Topic-Hierarchical.png" format="PNG" scalefit="1"/>
     </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
   </figure>
   <para>The figure above illustrates publishing messages with hierarchical routing keys. As before, the exchange routes each
    message to every bound queue whose binding key matches the routing key but as the binding keys contain wildcards, the
    wildcard rules described above apply.</para>
   <para>In the case illustrated, <literal>sub1</literal> has received the red and green message as &quot;<literal>news.uk</literal>&quot; and &quot;<literal>news.de</literal>&quot;
    match binding key &quot;<literal>news.#</literal>&quot;. The red message has also gone to <literal>sub2</literal> and <literal>sub3</literal> as it's routing key
    is matched exactly by &quot;<literal>news.uk</literal>&quot; and by &quot;<literal>*.uk</literal>&quot;.</para>
   <para>The routing key of the yellow message matches no binding keys, so the message is unroutable. It is handled as described
    in <xref linkend="Java-Broker-Concepts-Exchanges-UnroutableMessage"/>.</para>
   <figure>
    <title>Topic exchange - matching on JMS message selector</title>
    <mediaobject>
     <imageobject>
      <imagedata fileref="images/Exchange-Topic-JMSSelector.png" format="PNG" scalefit="1"/>
     </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
   </figure>
   <para>The figure above illustrates messages with properties published with routing key &quot;<literal>shipping</literal>&quot;.</para>
   <para>As before, the exchange routes each message to every bound queue whose binding key matches the routing key but as a JMS selector
    argument has been specified, the expression is evaluated against each matching message. Only messages whose message header values or properties
    match the expression are routed to the queue.</para>
   <para>In the case illustrated, <literal>sub1</literal> has received the yellow and blue message as their property &quot;<literal>area</literal>&quot;
    cause expression &quot;<literal>area in ('Forties', 'Cromarty')</literal>&quot; to evaluate true.  Similarly, the yellow message has also gone to
    <literal>gale_alert</literal> as its property &quot;<literal>speed</literal>&quot; causes expression &quot;<literal>speed &gt; 7 and speed &lt; 10</literal>&quot;
    to evaluate true.</para>
   <para>The properties of purple message cause no expressions to evaluate true, so the message is unroutable. It is handled as described in
    <xref linkend="Java-Broker-Concepts-Exchanges-UnroutableMessage"/>.</para>
  </section>
  <section id="Java-Broker-Concepts-Exchanges-Types-Fanout">
    <title>Fanout</title>
    <para>The fanout exchange type routes messages to all queues bound to the exchange, regardless of the message's routing key.</para>
    <para>Filter rules may be specified using a <link linkend="Java-Broker-Concepts-Exchanges-BindingArguments-JMSSelector">
    binding argument specifying a JMS message selector</link>.</para>
    <figure>
     <title>Fanout exchange</title>
     <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
       <imagedata fileref="images/Exchange-Fanout.png" format="PNG" scalefit="1"/>
      </imageobject>
     </mediaobject>
    </figure>
  </section>
  <section id="Java-Broker-Concepts-Exchanges-Types-Headers">
    <title>Headers</title>
    <para>The headers exchange type routes messages to queues based on header properties within the message. The message is passed to
     a queue if the header properties of the message satisfy the <link linkend="Java-Broker-Concepts-Exchanges-BindingArguments-x-match">
     x-match expression</link> specified by the binding arguments with which the queue was bound.
   </para>
  </section>
 </section>
 <section id="Java-Broker-Concepts-Exchanges-BindingArguments">
  <title>Binding Arguments</title>
  <para>Binding arguments are used by certain exchange types to further filter messages.</para>
  <section id="Java-Broker-Concepts-Exchanges-BindingArguments-JMSSelector">
   <title>JMS Selector</title>
   <para>The binding argument <literal>x-filter-jms-selector</literal> specifies a JMS selector conditional expression. The expression
    is written in terms of message header and message property names.  If the expression evaluates to true, the message is routed to the queue.
    This type of binding argument is understood by exchange types direct, topic and fanout.<footnote><para>
    This is a Qpid specific extension.</para></footnote>.</para>
  </section>
  <section id="Java-Broker-Concepts-Exchanges-BindingArguments-x-match">
   <title>x-match</title>
   <para>The binding argument <literal>x-match</literal> is understood by exchange type headers.  It can take two values, dictating how the
    rest of the name value pairs are treated during matching.</para>
   <itemizedlist>
     <listitem><para><literal>all</literal> implies that all the other pairs must match the headers property of a message for that message to be routed
      (i.e. an AND match)</para></listitem>
     <listitem><para><literal>any</literal> implies that the message should be routed if any of the fields in the headers property match one of the
      fields in the arguments table (i.e. an OR match)</para></listitem>
   </itemizedlist>
   <para>A field in the bind arguments matches a field in the message if either the field in the bind arguments has no value and a field of the
    same name is present in the message headers or if the field in the bind arguments has a value and a field of the same name exists in the
    message headers and has that same value.</para>
  </section>
 </section>
 <section id="Java-Broker-Concepts-Exchanges-UnroutableMessage">
  <title>Unrouteable Messages</title>
  <para>If an exchange is unable to route a message to any queues, the Broker will:
   <itemizedlist>
    <listitem><para>If using AMQP 0-10 protocol, and an alternate exchange has been set on the exchange, the message is routed to the alternate exchange.
    The alternate exchange routes the message according to its routing algorithm and its binding table.  If the messages is still unroutable,
    the message is discarded.</para></listitem>
    <listitem><para>If using AMQP protocols 0-8..0-9-1, and the publisher set the mandatory flag and the<link linkend="Java-Broker-Close-Connection-When-No-Route">
     close when no route</link> feature did not close the connection, the message is returned to the Producer.</para></listitem>
    <listitem><para>Otherwise, the message is discarded.</para></listitem>
   </itemizedlist>
  </para>
 </section>
</section>
