<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!--

 Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one
 or more contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file
 distributed with this work for additional information
 regarding copyright ownership.  The ASF licenses this file
 to you under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the
 "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance
 with the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at

   http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

 Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing,
 software distributed under the License is distributed on an
 "AS IS" BASIS, WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY
 KIND, either express or implied.  See the License for the
 specific language governing permissions and limitations
 under the License.

-->

<section id="Java-Broker-Runtime-Connection-Limit">
  <title>Connection Limits</title>
  <para>
     Each connection to the Broker consumes resources while it is connected. In order to protect
     the Broker against malfunctioning (or malicious) client processes, it is possible to limit the
     number of connections that can be active on any given port.
   </para>
   <para>
       Connection limits on AMQP ports are controlled by an attribute "maxOpenConnections" on
       the port. By default this takes the value of the context variable 
       <literal>qpid.port.max_open_connections</literal> which in itself is defaulted to the
       value <literal>-1</literal> meaning there is no limit.
   </para>
   <para>
       If the interpolated value of <literal>maxOpenConnections</literal> on an AMQP port is a
       positive integer, then when that many active connections have been established no new
       connections will be allowed (until an existing connection has been closed). Any such 
       rejection of a connection will be accompanied by the operational log message
       <link linkend="Java-Broker-Appendix-Operation-Logging-Message-PRT-1005">PRT-1005</link>.
   </para>
   <para>
       The context variable <literal>qpid.port.open_connections_warn_percent</literal> can be 
       used to control when a warning log message is generated as the number of open connections
       approaches the limit for the port. The default value of this variable is 
       <literal>80</literal> meaning that if more the number of open connections to the port
       has exceeded 80% of the given limit then the operatinal log message 
       <link linkend="Java-Broker-Appendix-Operation-Logging-Message-PRT-1004">PRT-1004</link>
       will be generated.
   </para>
</section>
